Frank C. Laubach Collection
Frank C. Laubach Collection
- Streamlined Reading Series Kinescope reels, 99 reels, each 29 minutes
  - Streamlined Reading #21 (Reel 27)
    Practice writing words by sound; top, tag, ted, bat, bob, big, leg, lap, lug, pig, pod.
  - Streamlined Reading #23 (Reel 28)
    Lesson 1 in Streamlined English; combining consonant sounds with i.
  - Streamlined Learning #18 (Reel 29)
    Practice writing words containing tall and short letters.
  - Streamlined Reading #17 (Reel 30)
    Practice writing small and capital letters B through Z and vowels; practice writing sounds th, sh, ch, wh, qu.
  - Streamlined Reading #19 (Reel 31)
    Review of Lessons 4 and 5; Chart 4, Z and vowels; Chart 5, x, qu, th, sh, ch, wh; Story 5, review of writing.
  - Streamlined Reading #4 (Reel 32)
    Chart 2, practice sounds J through Y; practice writing.
  - Streamlined Reading #31 (Reel 33)
    Review of Book 2; u; Lesson 1, 2, and 3.
  - Streamlined Reading #78 (Reel 34)
    Lesson 19, new sound, ou, ow; pictures; practice reading; practice writing.
  - Streamlined Reading #39 (Reel 35)
    Continue use of vowel A; practice reading apple sound of A; practice writing.
  - Streamlined Reading #37 (Reel 36)
    Lesson 5, vowel sound A as in apple; practice reading; practice writing.
  - Streamlined Reading #33 (Reel 37)
  - Streamlined Reading #35 (Reel 38)
    Lesson 4, letter E; review words with 'bed' sound of E; practice reading; sentence patterns; practice writing.
  - Streamlined Reading #44 (Reel 39)
    Review homework Lesson 5; Lesson 6; helping words; practice writing; practice saying first 15 letters of alphabet.
  - Streamlined Reading #47 (Reel 40)
    Review of AR sound; practice reading, practice writing.
  - Streamlined Reading #43 (Reel 41)
    Review of Lessons 4, 5, and 6; practice writing sounds TH, I, S.
  - Streamlined Reading #42 (Reel 42)
    Review lesson of capital and small letters; writing to music; how to sit and hold pencil; one demonstration writing letters A through R.
  - Streamlined Reading #45 (Reel 43)
    Writing and spelling; looking at pictures and writing a sentence about each picture.
  - Streamlined Reading #48 (Reel 44)
    Story of Dr. John; Lesson 8; the orange sound of the letter 0; pictures used for demonstration; practice reading; practice writing.
  - Streamlined Reading #46 (Reel 45)
    Review of sounds A as in apple and R; sound of both letters together; pictures used to demonstrate lesson; practice reading The Farm and The Farmer; contractions; practice writing.
  - Streamlined Reading #41 (Reel 46)
    Review of vowel sounds; pictures used to demonstrate short vowel sounds; practice writing; Y as a vowel; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #38 (Reel 47)
    Words containing the sound A as in apple; practice writing.
  - Streamlined Reading #34 (Reel 48)
    Review of vowel sound E as in egg; pictures used to demonstrate sound; practice reading; practice writing numbers 6, 7, 8 and 9.
  - Streamlined Reading #36 (Reel 49)
    Practice writing to learn to spell; pictures used often; practice with ell and ill combinations.
  - Streamlined Reading #40 (Reel 50)
    Lesson 6, commonly used words; parts of words; pass, ask, ance; pictures used throughout; ast, ath; practice reading; practice writing.
  - Streamlined Reading #49 (Reel 51)
    Practice writing last eight letters of alphabet, small and capitals, with music; numbers 1 through 9; practicing reciting ,alphabet through R; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #50 (Reel 52)
    Story of Dr. John; Lesson 9; New sound of UR, ER, and IR; practice with sound of R; practice reading and writing with new sound; pictures used to demonstrate sound.
  - Streamlined Reading #52 (Reel 53)
    Review of vowel sounds A as in apple, E as in egg, I as in in, O as in orange, and U as in up; Y sometimes as in city; practice reading and writing; pictures used to demonstrate; little repetition.
  - Streamlined Reading #55 (Reel 54)
    Recitation of alphabet; how to find names in a telephone directory; abbreviations; Mr., Mrs., and others; practice using the telephone; telephone dial used as demonstration tool; no pictures; emergency numbers.
  - Streamlined Reading #53 (Reel 55)
    Review of Lessons 8 and 9; sounds of o as in orange; U as in up, Y as in city; numbers, no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #56 (Reel 56)
    The long vowel sound of the letter E; ē, ee, ea, ey, e-e; different ways E may be written; pictures used; practice reading; practice writing.
  - Streamlined Reading #54 (Reel 57)
    Begin study of long vowel sounds; ā, ai, ay, a(k)e or a(m)e; different ways A may be written as a long vowel; pictures used; practice reading; practice writing.
  - Streamlined Reading #51 (Reel 58)
    Practice writing and spelling; use of new sound; er=ur, er, ir; letters rest on bottom line of writing; special letters go below bottom line.
  - Streamlined Reading #62 (Reel 59)
    Vowel sound of the letter O; five ways of writing long O, o, o-e, oe, cw, oa; practice reading; pictures used; practice writing.
  - Streamlined Reading #58 (Reel 60)
    Vowel sound of long I; Lesson 12; four ways to write the sound I, ide-ive-ine, igh, CI; practice reading; pictures used; practice writing.
  - Streamlined Reading #60 (Reel 61)
    Review of long vowel sounds; no pictures; sounds of A, I, E; dictation of sentences using those sounds; practice reading and writing.
  - Streamlined Reading #61 (Reel 62)
    Continuation of review of long vowel sounds of I, A, E; sentences dictated; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #59 (Reel 63)
    Completion of Lesson 12; practice reading sentences with long sounds of I; review of long vowel sounds of A, E, and I; practice writing; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #63 (Reel 64)
    Reading, groups of words; dictation of sentences to practice reading by groups; practice writing; Lesson 13; Long vowel sounds of O; ō, o-e, oe, ow, oa; practice writing words with long o vowel sound; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #64 (Reel 65)
    Lesson 14; story about farm life; study of sound of OR; practice reading, practice writing; pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #57 (Reel 66)
    Review of homework of Lessons 10 and 11; dictation and writing of words having long vowel sound E; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #72 (Reel 67)
    Lesson 17; sounds of diphthong AU, AW, ought, aught, alk; story with pictures; practice reading; practice writing.
  - Streamlined Reading #71 (Reel 68)
    Review of Lessons 13, 14, and 15; read sentences; Lesson 16; future tense; definitions of tense and verbs; practice writing; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #65 (Reel 69)
    Writing and spelling lesson about a farmer and his house; pictures used; sentences written about pictures; practice reading; practice writing.
  - Streamlined Reading #70 (Reel 70)
    Lesson 16; diphthong OO; future tense; pictures used; practice reading; practice writing.
  - Streamlined Reading #69 (Reel 71)
    Symbols, letters, pictures, and signs; pictures used; what symbols mean; practice writing words found on signs; color and shape of signs.
  - Streamlined Reading #66 (Reel 72)
    Lesson 15; story about a woman cook; sound of U as in put; UU as in cook, woman, good, looking, wood, etc.; pictures used to illustrate story; practice writing new words learned in lesson.
  - Streamlined Reading #68 (Reel 73)
    Review of long vowel sounds of 5, u as in put, 5; street signs; practice reading; practice writing; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #67 (Reel 74)
    Writing and spelling; dictation, hook, wool, hood, cookie, stood, and woodcarver; practice writing sentences using oo sound; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #73 (Reel 75)
    Going over homework sentences of Lesson 16; review using sentences to illustrate three sound alike words, to, two, too; practice reading and writing; dictation; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #79 (Reel 76)
    Dictation; words having long u sound; practice reading and writing; no pictures; often used together words, "let us go."
  - Streamlined Reading #75 (Reel 77)
    Lesson helping to spell sound au, aw, ought, aught, alk; sentences illustrating these sounds; practice reading and writing; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #77 (Reel 78)
    Review sentences of Lesson 17; ai, oo, ar, ee, uu; practice reading and writing; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #74 (Reel 79)
    Lesson 18; long vowel sound of E, ue, ew, use, ure; practice reading and writing; dictation story illustrating sound; pictures used.
  - Streamlined Reading #76 (Reel 80)
    Review of Lesson 16; homework; Number 17; word list; verbs; helping words; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #80 (Reel 81)
    Continuation of Lesson 19; five new words; nouns, vowels, consonants, syllables, accent; practice writing vowels; practice writing consonants; definition of syllables; practice writing syllables; rules about vowel sounds; definition of accent; practice writing accent; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #88 (Reel 82)
    More about consonants; unvoiced letters t, p, k, ch, f, s, etc; voiced letters b, d, g, j, v, z; voiced letters through the nose, m, n, ng; silent letters; two ways to pronounce s; rules; exceptions; practice reading and writing; story of three Roberts; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #87 (Reel 83)
    Rules governing pronunciation of vowels; diphthongs; practice reading and writing; dictation of sentences having one vowel words and two vowel words; fords for ex. pin and pine, not and note, cap and cape; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #82 (Reel 84)
    Lesson 20; new sound of and oy; pictures used to illustrate words having the new sound; story using new sound; practice reading and writing.
  - Streamlined Reading #83 (Reel 85)
    How to use dictionary; parts of words; syllables, accents, hyphen; definitions of these words; pen-man-ship, friend-ly; one syllable words; how they are pronounced; practice reading, writing, and pronouncing one or more syllable words; sign indicating short vowel sound, e.g., pen; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #85 (Reel 86)
    Review of Lessons 18, 19 and 20; filling in blanks in sentences; practice reading sentences; practice in s sound and of and oy sounds; practice writing sentences using these sounds; exclamation mark.
  - Streamlined Reading #84 (Reel 87)
    Review of Lessons 18, 19 and 20; practice reading words from word lists; things; verbs; helping words; nouns; practice reading sentences; practice writing.
  - Streamlined Reading #86 (Reel 88)
    Review of long vowel sounds; 5, ay, ai, a/e; baby, play, braid, face; e, e-e, ee, ea, ey; be, Pete, tree, read, key; i, i-e, igh, y; child, fine, bright, cry; 6, o-e, oe, ow, oa; old, home, pictures; u, ue, ew, u-e; due, news, cure; Y, by; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #81 (Reel 89)
    The dictionary; how to use it; entry words; alphabetical order; practice putting words in alphabetical order by their second letter; same by third letter; same by fourth letter; guide words; vocabulary; phonetic spelling, n, noun, meanings of words; pronunciation; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #94 (Reel 90)
    Canister 91 Two sounds of g, hard and soft; go, gem; rules governing usage; practice reading and writing sentences with the two sounds of g; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #91 (Reel 91)
    Help in word recognition; explanation pronouncing ch; three ways to pronounce ch; ch as pronounced in child and such; exception is stomach; tch is always soft as in catch or kitchen; beginning ch sound three ways; child, Christmas, chef; rules governing sounds of ch; before a vowel, when in middle of a word, names of people with ch in middle; before 1 and r; s before ch; ch = sh in words coming from French.
  - Streamlined Reading #92 (Reel 92)
    Th and tion; this thing; voiced and unvoiced; practice with th as beginning sound; tion and sion = shun sound; practice; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #89 (Reel 93)
    Short review of voiced and unvoiced letters; quiz; p, unvoiced, z; voiced, ten examples; no pictures; review of silent letters; pronunciations of s.
  - Streamlined Reading #93 (Reel 94)
    Rules about sounds of the letter c; when c is before the letters e, i, or y it has soft sound as s in snake; two ways to pronounce c; soft as soft s and hard as in k; when c is before any letter except above letters it has hard sound; ch as sh; practice in dictation; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #95 (Reel 95)
    Sounds of ng; three rules; as in king and ring; voiced through nose; practice pronouncing examples ng in the middle of a word as in finger, angry and other examples; practice; exceptions to the rules; long, longer, longest; strong and young, etc. nge is pronounced like nje; change, danger, edge, strange, etc.; practice; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #97
    Questions about three stories; study of word lists; new words learned; practice reading, writing, spelling; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #98
    The last lesson; 22 new words which break rules; pronunciation; believe, busy, business, heaven, leather, opposite, pearl, tongue, pleasant, building, island, creased, relief, religion, rough, cough, sew, spread, sword, thread, carriage, youth; all these words break a rule; words with unnecessary a, earth, heaven, pearl, dean, instead, etc.; pronunciation of ough; five ways, though, rough, cough, plough, through; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #96
    Rules how consonants can change sounds of vowels; ong, awng; long, belong, strong, etc.; all, awl; all words that come from all are spelled al, already, almost, etc., except shall; war and wal, a, aw, war, wall, etc.; double consonants following vowels give vowel short sound; manner, etc.; dividing words with double consonants into syllables; practice writing; silent letters; w before r and k and g silent in front of n; silent letters in front of t; o in front of us; 1 in front of k; no pictures.
  - Streamlined Reading #90
    Making longer words by adding endings; ed, three ways of pronouncing ed; ed as in lifted, d as in called, and t as in talked; ed when following d or t; d when it follows voiced letters, b, e, g, j, 1, m, n, o, r, v, n, y, z; t when it follows unvoiced letters, ch, f, k, p, sh, x, ss; quiz.